Guide to the Hovander Family and Park Papers 1844-1996
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Hovander Family and Park Papers
1844-1996
1871-1996
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0022hovander
Hovander Family--Archives
12.6 Linear Ft. 27 Boxes 11 Oversize Folders
This collection consists of papers generated by the Hovander family, prominent local Whatcom County pioneers who immigrated to Ferndale in the early 1900's. The head of the family, Hokan Hovander, was a well-known architect in Sweden who also did substantial architectural work for the city of Chicago after the 1871 fire. He also designed the Hovander Homestead house. Included are documents generated by researchers and Hovander/Tennant Lake park staff regarding the Hovander family. These documents were subsequently used by the park interpretive center and tour guides.
Hokan (Hovander) Olsson was born on December 6, 1841, near Malmo, Sweden. Hokan's parents, Ola Persson and Else Nilsdatter, were semi-prosperous tenant farmers who struggled to support Hokan and his eight siblings, including Hokan's twin brother Christian. In 19th Century Sweden, tenant farming was a particularly difficult livelihood for most families. Only 10% of Sweden's land was arable and suitable for farming. In addition, Swedish laws stipulated that landowners must maintain their land parcels as a unit and were prohibited from dividing lands among heirs. As a result, many younger sons, such as Hokan, chose to migrate to large cities like Stockholm in search of more viable vocational prospects. Once in Stockholm, Hokan became an apprentice bricklayer by day and studied architecture in the evening. Sometime during the 1860s, Hokan changed his surname from Olsson to Hafvander (later Havander or Hovander). This name change probably reflected Hokan's desire to facilitate his architectural career by choosing a more distinctive name than the common "Olsson."
In 1865, Hokan and his brother Christian left Sweden and travelled first to Australia and New Zealand and then to the United States, where they established separate homesteads in Kansas. Christian chose to remain in Kansas, but Hokan continued his travels in the U.S., eventually migrating to Chicago. While in Chicago, Hokan returned to his chosen profession of architecture. In the wake of the devastating fire of 1871, he found ample opportunity to hone his architectural skills as he helped to rebuild the city. He also worked along the West Coast in San Francisco, Portland, and Seattle.
In 1879, He returned to Sweden and married Louisa Leontine Johandatter Lof and settled into family life and an architectural career. Although he was not officially licensed as an architect in Sweden, this period was particularly prolific for Hokan, and he completed many building and design projects during this time. Hokan's work in Sweden culminated with the creation of his most famous work, the "Mansion," a large residential building in Stockholm created in the Beaux Arts style.
In 1885, Hokan succumbed to an episode of tuberculosis and was advised to spend some time in a warmer climate. Hokan, Leontine and their children, Hugo, Elsa and Otis embarked on a world cruise, traveling from Sweden to Australia and finally to San Francisco. In California, Elsa met her future husband, Karl Stromee. The Stromees and other transplanted Swedes convinced the Hovanders that immigration to the U.S. would be beneficial to both Hokan's health and the future of the children. After returning to Sweden and selling the "Mansion", the Hovander family set sail for New Zealand in 1896. By then, the family had grown to include three more children: Angelo, Charles and Ada.
The Hovander family reached Seattle by 1897 but chose not to stay, complaining of noise and price inflation caused by Gold Rush fever. Instead, the family migrated north to Whatcom County. The Hovanders paid Betsey Nielson $4000 in gold coin for 60 acres near Ferndale, which included two small cabins, some farm implements, and a few livestock. In 1899, the last Hovander child, Vera, was born in one of the cabins. Hokan designed a house and barn based on traditional Scandinavian architectural features but which also incorporated building techniques learned while working in the U.S. These buildings still stand on the property today.
Hokan died in 1915 of chronic myocarditis, fifteen years after work on the house was completed. Leontine died in 1936, as a result of complications from diabetes. All the children married, except for Otis. Otis, a friendly and colorful local personality with wide and varied interests, is well represented in the family papers. He was an avid stamp collector and maintained a large correspondence with fellow collectors. Otis loved antique cars and belonged to a vintage car club. He was a member of the Knights of Pythias and was also interested in politics and automobile safety issues. Otis also enjoyed playing musical instruments and once requested an audition with the Original Amateur Hour in New York City. Otis shared the Hovander House with widowed sister Elsa from 1946 until her death in 1961. Otis remained in the house until 1969, when he moved into the Lynden Rest home where he resided until his death in 1979.
The papers of Elsa Hovander Stromee are also well represented in this collection. Elsa's husband Karl owned and ran the Economy Print Shop in San Bernardino, California, which employed Japanese and Chinese Americans and nationals. Karl died in 1946, after which Elsa moved back to Whatcom County to live with Otis.
The Whatcom County Parks and Recreation Board purchased the Hovander property for $60,000 in 1969. Upon acquisition, the Parks Department repainted and refurbished the buildings and continues to maintain the house today. A small working farmyard adjacent to the house was restocked with typical farm animals. Farm implements were collected from many different sources and displayed in the barn along with identifying labels. The house and grounds are open to visitors.
The Hovander Family and Park Papers consist of papers created by the Hovander family as well as material generated by Hovander Homestead Park staff. The bulk of the Hovander family materials were created and collected by Hokan, Elsa, and Otis Hovander, with other family members making up the remainder.
This collection includes correspondence, architectural drawings, maps, notes and writings, newspaper clippings, canceled checks, deposit slips, bank statements, tax records, legal documents, pamphlets & broadsides, photographs, Park reference materials and oral histories. A few of these oral histories include an audiocassette and full transcript, while most have only a short transcript. Roughly half of the total family correspondence is written in Swedish without accompanying translations. The other subseries also contain some Swedish language materials.
The photographs included in this collection provide not only a detailed account of the lives of the Hovander family, but also depict life on the farm and the many travels taken by members of the family. Included are many photographs of Paris, Germany, and Stockholm at the turn of the 20th century, as well as the family's multiple trips to San Francisco and southern California in the early half of that century. Early events in Whatcom County are also included. Parades, photographs of schools, and other views of downtown Bellingham and portions of Ferndale are numerous within the collection.
The Hovander Family and Park Papers are organized in accordance with the following series and sub-series arrangement:
Series I: Hovander Family Papers 1871-1973
Subseries 1. Biographical Papers
Subseries 2. Correspondence
Subseries 3. Financial Records
Subseries 4. Legal Records
Subseries 5.Other Family Papers
Subseries 6. Printed Materials
Subseries 7. Photographs
Subseries 8. Architectural Drawings & Maps
Series II: Hovander Park Interpretive Materials 1940-1996
Subseries 1. General Research
Subseries 2. Oral Histories
The collection is open to the public.
The Whatcom County Parks and Recreation Board purchased the Hovander farm in 1969 and gained possession of the Hovander Family Papers.
Due to archivally inadequate storage facilities the Parks Department subsequently donated the Hovander Family Papers as well as materials generated by the Hovander Homestead Park staff to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies in 2001 and 2002.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Hovander, Hokan, 1847-1915--Archives.; Hovander, Elsa--Archives.; Hovander, Otis--Archives.
Hovander Family--Archives.
Hovander Homestead Park.
Frontier and pioneer life--Washington (State)--Whatcom County--Sources; Family farms--Washington (State)--Whatcom County--History--Sources; Agriculture--Washington (State)--Whatcom County--History--Sources; Barns--Washington (State)--Whatcom County; Architecture--Washington (State)--Whatcom County
Washington (State)--History--Sources; Ferndale (Wash.)--History--Sources
Records (Documents); Photographs
Washington (State); Architectural Drawings; Pioneers; Oral Histories; Photographs; Maps; Agriculture; Architecture; Home and Family; Parks and Playgrounds
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Hovander Family Papers, 1801-1973; Series I
  - Biographical Papers, 1890-1973; Sub-series 1
    - Family History Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - General Family - Personal Papers and Information, 1919-1931 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Hovander Histories (written by family members), circa 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Hokan Hovander - Personal Papers and Information (With photograph), 1890-1915 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Otis Hovander - Personal Papers and Information, 1918-1963 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1970; Sub-series 2
    - Letters
      - Elsa (Hovander) Stromee (Some letters are in Swedish)
        - Letters, 1900-1942 (Box-folder 1/6)
        - Letters, 1943-1955 (Box-folder 1/7)
        - Letters, undated; circa 1876-1961 (Box-folder 1/8)
        - Letters regarding courtship with Karl Stromee, circa 1910s (Box-folder 1/9)
        - WWI Correspondence with Charles Hovander, 1919 (Box-folder 1/10)
        - Correspondence with Karl Stromee, 1900-1916 (Box-folder 1/11)
        - Correspondence with Karl Stromee, 1876-1946; Undated (Box-folder 1/12)
      - General Family Correspondence (some letters are in Swedish)
        - Correspondence, 1876-1937 (Box-folder 1/13)
        - Correspondence, Undated (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Hokan Hovander (Some letters are in Swedish)
        - Letters, 1879-1909 (Box-folder 2/1)
        - Letters, 1910-1914 (Box-folder 2/2)
        - Letters, Undated; circa 1876-1915 (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Leontine Hovander (Some letters are in Swedish)
        - Letters, 1903-1935 (Box-folder 2/4)
        - Letters, Undated; circa 1876-1936 (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Otis Hovander (Some letters are in Swedish and include photographs)
        - Letters, 1898-1950 (Box-folder 2/6)
        - Letters, 1951-1970 (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Letters, Undated (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Vera (Hovander) Ralston
        - Letters, 1919-1929 (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Letters, Undated; circa 1876-1929 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Cards & Notes
      - Christmas and New Year, 1897-1952 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Christmas and New Year, 1953-1963 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Christmas and New Year, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Christmas and New Year, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Christmas and New Year, Undated (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Christmas and New Year, Undated (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Christmas and New Year, Undated (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Other Holidays, 1884-1970 (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Other Holidays, Undated (Box-folder 4/4)
      - Other Holidays, Undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Postcards, 1890-1912 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Postcards, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Postcards, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Postcards, 1920-1939 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Postcards, 1940-1966 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Postcards, Undated (Box-folder 6/2 - 6/5)
    - Postcards, Undated (Box-folder 7/1 - 7/4)
    - Postcards on Leather, 1906-1912 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Postcards-Whatcom County and Skagit County Subjects, 1909-1916 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Postcards & Souvenir Cards, 1907-1946 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Financial Records, 1873-1969; Sub-series 3
    - Bank Documents, 1920-1966 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Bank Statements, 1929-1969 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1873-1921 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1925 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1925 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1926 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1930-1939 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1950-1956 (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Bills & Receipts, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Bills & Receipts, Undated (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Certificates of Transfer and Registry (Livestock), 1912 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Checks, 1909-1915 (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Checks, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Checks, 1924-1926 (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Checks, 1927-1930 (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Checks, 1931-1969 (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Check Stubs, 1908-1951 (Box-folder 10/7)
    - Contracts, Leases & Mortgages, 1880-1967 (Box-folder 10/8)
    - Farm Account Files, 1933-1953 (Box-folder 10/9)
    - Financial Correspondence, 1914-1967 (Box-folder 10/10)
    - Insurance Files, 1920-1972 (Box-folder 11/1)
    - Memorandum/Statement of Delinquent Taxes, 1902-1927 (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Notes, Undated (Box-folder 11/3)
    - Tax Records, 1894-1958 (Box-folder 11/4)
    - War Department Land Lease, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Legal Records, 1908-1968; Sub-series 4
    - Family Legal Correspondence, 1908-1968 (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Hilda Dupont (Leontine's sister) Will Dispute - Correspondence, 1929-1945 (Box-folder 12/2)
    - Hilda Dupont (Leontine's sister) Will Dispute - Court and Attorney Documents, 1938-1946 (Box-folder 12/3)
    - Hilda Dupont (Leontine's sister) Will Dispute - Notes and Clippings, circa 1940s (Box-folder 12/4)
    - Hovander (Otis) vs. Dorr - Correspondence and Court Documents, 1948 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Other Family Papers, 1853-1962; Sub-series 5
    - General Family
      - Drawings and Artwork, Undated (Box-folder 12/6)
      - Papers and Notes, 1853-1962 (Box-folder 12/7)
      - Papers and Notes, Undated; circa 1895-1950 (Box-folder 12/8)
      - Hovander children schoolwork and related materials, circa 1890s-1920s (Box-folder 12/9)
      - John Nielson materials, circa 1890s (Box-folder 12/10)
      - Notebooks and Calendars/Address Books, circa 1860s-1920s (Box-folder 12/11)
      - Notebooks and Calendars/Address Books, Undated (Box-folder 12/12)
    - Otis Hovander
      - Census Enumerator Materials, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 13/1)
      - Bills and Receipts of R.C. “Kernel” Moseley, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 13/2)
      - General correspondence of R.C. “Kernel” Moseley, 1920-1950 (Box-folder 13/3)
      - Legal Correspondence and Documents of R.C. “Kernel” Moseley, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Vera Hovander - Schoolwork and Related Materials, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 13/5)
    - Vera Hovander - Schoolwork and Related Materials, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - Printed Materials, 1801-1969; Sub-series 6
    - Articles, 1929-1943 (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Clippings in English, 1897-1969 (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Clippings in English, 1946-1953 (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Clippings in English, Undated (Box-folder 14/4)
    - Clippings in Swedish, 1910-1966 (Box-folder 14/5)
    - Clippings of Hovander Family Members, 1906-1944 (Box-folder 14/6)
    - Clipping regarding Labor Exchange Bond, 1895 (Box-folder 14/7)
    - Pamphlets and Broadsides
      - Advertising, circa 1920s-1960s (Box-folder 14/8)
      - Advertising, circa 1920s-1960s (Box-folder 14/9)
      - Arts and Crafts, 1900-1940s (Box-folder 14/10)
      - Farming, 1900-1940s (Box-folder 14/11)
      - General, 1889-1967 (Box-folder 15/1)
      - General, 1889-1967 (Box-folder 15/2)
      - Health Issues, 1923-1967 (Box-folder 15/3)
      - Political, circa 1940s-1960s (Box-folder 15/4)
      - “Puget Sound Times” (vintage car club), circa 1960s (Box-folder 15/5)
      - Religious, 1908-1960 (Box-folder 15/6)
      - Special Occasions, 1911-1969 (Box-folder 15/7)
    - Printed Art, circa 1900s-1950s (Box-folder 16/1)
    - Printed Art, circa 1900s-1950s (Box-folder 16/2)
    - Printed Materials (7 items), 1801-1894 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s; Sub-series 7
    - Negatives, circa 1890s-1950s (Box-folder 16/3)
    - Negatives, circa 1890s-1950s (Box-folder 16/4)
    - Negatives, circa 1890s-1950s (Box-folder 16/5)
    - Negatives, circa 1890s-1950s (Box-folder 16/6)
    - Albums
      - Hovander Family & Farm, circa 1920s (Box-folder 17/1)
      - Hovander Family & Farm, circa 1920s (Box-folder 17/2)
      - 1925-1926 (Box-folder 17/3)
      - Europe & U.S. East Coast, 1904-1908 (Box-folder 18/1)
      - Hovander Family & Farm, 1917 (Box-folder 18/2)
      - Hovander Family & Farm, circa 1910s-1920s (Box-folder 18/3)
      - Stromee, Elsa (Hovander) family and friends, circa 1910s-1920s (Box-folder 19/1)
    - Photos of Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/1)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/2)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/3)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/4)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/5)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/6)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/7)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/8)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 20/9)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/1)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/2)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/3)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/4)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/5)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/6)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/7)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/8)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/9)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/10)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/11)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/12)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/13)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/14)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/15)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/16)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 21/17)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 22/1)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 22/2)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 22/3)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 22/4)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 23/1)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 23/2)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 23/3)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 23/4)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 23/5)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 24/1)
      - Hovander Family, Farm, & Travels, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 24/2)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/1)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/2)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/3)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/4)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/5)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/6)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/7)
      - Oversize Photographs, circa 1870s-1950s (Box-folder 25/8)
      - Oversize Photograph - "Twenty-Eighth Annual Session, Washington State Grange - P of H, Burlington, Washington", 1916 June 6-9 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Architectural Drawings and Maps, 1831-1910; Sub-series 8
    Many of these drawings and maps are extremely fragile. Most of the notes and text accompanying the drawings and maps are in Swedish. U.S. and Canadian maps are now located in the Miscellaneous Map Collection at the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies. See locator #2-18, 6-10, 6-11 and 8-88.
    - Architectural Drawings - Hovander House and Farm (18 items), 1890-1900s (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Architectural Drawings - Hovander House and Farm (15 items), 1890-1900s (Oversize-folder 4)
    - Architectural Drawings - Stockholm "Mansion" (6 items), circa 1880s (Oversize-folder 5)
    - Architectural Drawings - Stockholm "Mansion" (24 items), circa 1880s (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Architectural Drawings - Stockholm "Mansion"(24 items), circa 1880s (Oversize-folder 7)
    - Architectural Drawings - Miscellaneous (27 items), circa 1880s-1910s (Oversize-folder 8)
    - Maps – Europe, Russia and New Zealand (17 items), 1831-1896 (Oversize-folder 9)
    - Maps – Sweden (16 items), 1844-1873 (Oversize-folder 10)
- Hovander Park Interpretive Materials, circa 1940s-1996; Series II
  - General Research, circa 1940s-1994; Sub-series 1
    - Artifacts on Loan, circa 1970s (Box-folder 26/1)
    - Catalog Cards, circa 1970s (Box-folder 26/2)
    - Early Maps, circa 1980s (Box-folder 26/3)
    - Farm Deed Files, circa 1990s (Box-folder 26/4)
    - Farm Equipment Files, circa 1940-1960s (Box-folder 26/5)
    - Goran Rygert Correspondence and Notes, 1995 (Box-folder 26/6)
    - Homestead Research Paper, circa 1980s (Box-folder 26/7)
    - Hovander Farm Equipment (Includes photos), circa 1980s (Box-folder 26/8)
    - Hovander Files, 1980-1995 (Box-folder 26/9)
    - "Hovander Legacy, The" (DVD), circa 2003 (Box-folder 26/10)
    - Manuals, circa 1970-1980 (Box-folder 26/11)
    - Mt. Baker Files, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 27/1)
    - National Park Service Material, 1980 (Box-folder 27/2)
    - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1970s (Box-folder 27/3)
    - Nooksack Files, 1985-1995 (Box-folder 27/4)
    - Photographs, circa 1970s (Box-folder 27/5)
    - Pioneer Park Files, 1987-1996 (Box-folder 27/6)
    - Reference Materials, circa 1970-1980s (Box-folder 27/7)
    - Reference Notes, circa 1970s-1980s (Box-folder 27/8)
    - RSVP (Retired Senior Volunteer Program) Files, circa 1980s (Box-folder 27/9)
    - Slide Presentation, circa 1990s (Box-folder 27/10)
    - Tennant Files, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 27/11)
    - Hovander Park Interpretive Materials (6 items), circa 1970s (Oversize-folder 11)